<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sermon I. on Phil. IV. 11.</title>
            <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5131C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49197132</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 49197132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2257:4b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sermon I. on Phil. IV. 11.</title>
                  <author>Stafford, Richard, 1663-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Written by Richard Stafford"-- P. 24.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams's Library (London).</note>
                  <note>With: The exceeding great comfort and benefit of having walked before God in truth, and with a perfect heart / by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ... MDCXCIX [1699] -- The necessity of keeping still unto the ordinances of religion. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., 1698 (Wing S5126) -- A sermon on 2 Cor. 2. XI / written by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., MDCXCVIII [1698] (Wing S5131B) -- The absolute truth, and utmost certainty of the word of God / by Richard Stafford. London : Printed ... by Ralph Simpson ..., MDCXCIX [1699] (Wing S5107F) -- Hear this word, o ye princes, ye priests and people of England. [London : s.n., 1698] (Wing S5120).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians, IV, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151376:1"/>
            <head>SERMON I. ON Phil. IV. 11. <hi>For I have Learned in whatſoever State 1 am, therewith to be Content.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Drift and Deſign of all Preaching the Word is, that People may <hi>ceaſe to do Evil</hi> and <hi>Learn to do well,</hi> as much as ever they can. And inaſmuch as a great deal of ſin is occaſioned through diſtruſt, murmuring, concerning the exceeding Sinfulneſs and Provocation whereof ye may read in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places in the Book of <hi>Numbers,</hi> our Hearts fretting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord: <hi>(The Fooliſhneſs of Man perverteth his way, and his heart fretteth againſt the Lord</hi> Coveteouſneſs and ſuch like. And on the other hand, that we may <hi>finiſh our Courſe with joy, even when Bonds and Afflictions abide us in every place.</hi> And the ſeveral ſevere and harſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of Providence which befall us (they being ſo many Exerciſes and Tryals whereby God holds his Servants in warfare here on Earth) do not move us, nor yet hinder us, but that we may Nevertheleſs finiſh the Miniſtry which we have received of the Lord Jeſus, to teſtify the Goſpel of the Grace of God; And that no outward thing whatever which ſhall happen unto Men, may hinder them in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of, and finiſhing that work which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them ſeverally on this Earth for to do; <hi>That ye may truſt in the Lord and do Good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the Land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed.</hi> And perform every
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151376:2"/> tittle of your reſpective Duties in whatever Vocation or Calling, Trade or Employment, State or Condition of Life God hath placed ye in, Come Proſperity or Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whether ye receive Good, or Evil things from the Hands of God, That ye may ſtill in all the ſeveral Periods and Stages of your enſuing life, whether it be up Hill or on ſmooth Ground, in dirty or clean way drive at theſe two ends, eſchew Evil and do Good, bearing the ſame ſtill in Mind and Practiſing the ſame, Theſe and ſuch like are the reaſons of my choice to Diſcourſe on this Subject, <hi>For I have Learned in whatſoever State I am in, therewith to be Content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are the Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which he brings in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the occaſion of an Act of <hi>Liberality</hi> which the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſhewed towards him; which they would have done before, but they lacked opportunity, and at laſt they did it. Thus much is ſignified from thoſe words immediately foregoing our Text. <hi>But I rejoyced in the Lord Greath, that now at the laſt your care of me hath flouriſhed again; wherein ye alſo were careful but ye lacked opportunity. No that I ſpeak in reſpect of want.</hi> Which words do carry an Innuendo, Intimation or Meaning, tho he doth not affirm it plainly through modeſty and ſhame by Nature, which doth uſually accompany that condition of his want. Or rather, he doth afterwards ſo expreſs himſelf, that wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would be want to others was none to him; Becauſe by this excellent Grace of Contentation he had ſo made it that want was as it were no want unto him. <hi>Not that I ſpeak in reſpect of want,</hi> (Why ſhould he uſe this Phraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Manner of Speech unleſs there was ſomething in it. <hi>In verſe</hi> 16. He ſpeaks out plainly, <hi>Ye ſent once and agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto my neceſſity)</hi> For I have Learned in whatſoever Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I am in therewith to be Content.</p>
            <p>Brethren, It is no new or ſtrange thing for the Saint and Servants of God to be in Want, Need, or Poverty for this is what happened to others of former Generation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in other Countreys. A remarkable Inſtance and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof was the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> as he giveth us her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to underſtand, as alſo in other places of his Epiſtles. <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there cried a certain Woman of the Wives of the Sons of the Prophets unto</hi> Eliſha, <hi>ſaying, thy Servant, my Husband i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dead, and thou knoweſt that thy Servant did fear the Lord
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151376:2"/> and the Creditor is come to take unto him my two Sons to be Bondmen, whereupon</hi> Eliſha <hi>did work a Miracle to pay that debt,</hi> 2 Kings 4. 1. Here was one that did fear the Lord and yet was in debt. The time would fail me to tell of all thoſe his Servants and Prophets that were under the Old Teſtament Diſpenſation, of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and the Poor Saints (to whom it is ſaid in an eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>the Goſpel is Preached)</hi> who have been ſince that time in the World, who were but Poor and Low in Eſtate as to this Worlds Goods. The <hi>Patriarke Jacob</hi> was hardly put to his ſhifts, and yet he found ſuſtenance by the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or providing of Almighty God; which he doth inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and moſt thankfully acknowledge upon his Death Bed, <hi>God before whom my Fathers.</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Iſaac <hi>did walk, the God which fed me all along unto this Day.</hi> Gen. 48. 15. This anſwered unto that Vow, which he Vowed in the times of his Travels and Pilgrimage, we read in <hi>Gen. 28. 20. If God will be with me in the way that I go, and will give me Bread to Eat and Raiment to put on, ſo that I come again to my Fathers Houſe in. Peace, then ſhall the Lord be my God.</hi> Which kind of Expreſſion then uttered, did carry with it ſome kind of fear and diſtruſt, as alſo therein was contained Prayer, Truſt and Confidence. The <hi>Patriarke</hi> Goes on to add, <hi>The Angel which redeemed me from all Evil,</hi> Gen. 48. 16. Notwithſtanding his ſaying of this, Nevertheleſs, he did meet with Afflictions and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs; But the Angel of the Lord, even at the very ſame time did preſerve him from the Evil of thoſe Afflictions; and afterwards redeemed him utterly from the afflictions and troubles themſelves. Here it may be asked, What is the <hi>Evil of Afflictions?</hi> It is either ſin, or to be made mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable by them; which the true Saint or Servant of God is not, nor yet doth he give way unto the other, in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever affliction doth befall or happen unto him. It is an excellent Character that is left recorded of <hi>Job,</hi> that amidſt all his Griefs and Calamities: <hi>In all this Job ſinned not, nor charged God fooliſhly,</hi> Job 1. 22. And ſo it is with every one of us, that do ſerve and fear him. God doth not ſo much preſerve us from Afflictions and Troubles; for he doth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, yea, and order them to fall upon us: But then it is, that he doth redeem us from all Evil, when amidſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pain, Smart and Vexation of them, In all this we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151376:3"/> ſin not, nor yet leave Duty undone, nor yet charge God fooliſhly. So that no hard thoughts do ariſe in our minds, nor yet do our hearts fret againſt the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But even unto this day when</hi> Moſes <hi>is Read</hi> (and ſo it is at this Day, when the Goſpel of Chriſt is Read) <hi>the Veil is upon their Heart,</hi> 2 Cor. 3. 15. <hi>Seeing many things, but thou obſerveſt not,</hi> Iſa. 42, 20. And ſo People read many things in the Scriptures, the Book of the Lord, but they <hi>Obſerve them not.</hi> They do not confer experiences in their own Souls, and commune and ſearch with their own Spirit how it is there. The Lord hath given me that knowledge, even from the times of my Youth, and the days of my former Years, that what I did Read in that Book, I ſhould apply unto my ſelf. And I remember particularly, that above ten Years ſince, when I was in my Chamber and ſtill, as it is written, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think that ye have Eternal Life,</hi> John 5. 39. <hi>Of which Salvation the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have enquired and ſearched diligently, ſearching what, or what manner of time, the Spirit of Chriſt did ſignifie-</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 10. 11. So it was, That not upon the outward cuſtomary or curſory reading, but upon the <hi>ſearching</hi> (Marke that) yea upon the <hi>ſearching Diligently</hi> of the Scriptures I found, how that the whole Current and Stream of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and good things of God were therein declared, and made unto the Poor and Needy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Needy ſhall not alway be forgotten, the expectation of the Poor ſhall not periſh for ever,</hi> Pſal. 9. 18. <hi>For the Oppreſſion of the Poor, for the Sighing of the Needy, now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, I will ſet him in Safety from him that puffeth at him</hi> Pſal. 12. 5. <hi>I know that the Lord will maintain the Cauſe of the Afflicted, and the Right of the Poor,</hi> Pſal. 140. 12. <hi>When the Poor and Needy ſeek Water and there is none, I the Lord will hear them, I the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>will not forſake them,</hi> Iſa. 41. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel unto the Poor,</hi> Luke. 4. 18. <hi>Bleſſed be ye Poor, for your is the Kingdom of God,</hi> Luke, 6. 20. <hi>Hath not God choſen the Poor of this World, Rich in Faith, and Heirs of the Kingdom which he hath Promiſed to them that Love him,</hi> James. 2, 5. There are Innumerable other places of Scripture to the ſame purpoſe. But Obſerve here the Limitation and Reſtriction; for the divinely Inſpired Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſtle doth not here ſay, the Lord hath choſen all the Poor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151376:3"/> of this World, but only thoſe, who (as the Words imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately following add) are <hi>Rich in Faith and Heirs of the Kingdom which he hath Promiſed to them that Love him.</hi> So that none of the good things afore or hereafter mentioned, do belong to ſuch Poor as are Ungodly, Ignorant or Sinners.</p>
            <p>Again, in the ſame Scriptures of Truth, there are many Evil things ſpoken againſt the Rich of the People. <hi>But ye have deſpiſed the Poor. Do not Rich Men oppreſs you, and draw you before the Judgment Seat? Doe they not Blaſpheme that Worthy Name by the which ye are called?</hi> James. 2, 6, 7. <hi>Go to now ye Rich Men, Weep and Howl for your Miſeries that ſhall come upon you. Your Riches are corrupted and your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are moth eaten. Your Gold and Silver is Cankered, and the Ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſs againſt you and ſhall eat your Fleſh as it were Fire. Ye have heaped Treaſure together for the laſt Dayes: ye have lived in pleaſure on the Earth, ye have Nouriſhed your Hearts as in a Day of Slaughter,</hi> James, 5, 1, 2, 5. <hi>Wo unto you that are Rich, for you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived your Conſolation,</hi> Luke. 6. 24. <hi>Wo unto them that joyn Houſe to Houſe that lay, Field to Field—Therefore Hell hath enlarged her ſelf and opened her Mouth without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: And their Glory, and their Multitude, and their Pomp, and he that rejoyceth, ſhall deſcend into it, Iſa.</hi> 5. 8, 14. Now <hi>the Scripture ſaith nothing in vain;</hi> for all of it, even to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tittle muſt be fulfilled; and that Wo which is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Pronounced againſt them, and hangs over their Head, will at length fall down upon them in Puniſhment and Miſery. <hi>They are incloſed in their own fat, with their Mouth they ſpeak proudly.—Deliver my Soul</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi> by the Spirit) <hi>from the Wicked, which is thy Sword, from Men which are thy Hand, O Lord, from Men of the World, which have their Portion in this Life, and whoſe Belly thou filleſt with thy hid Treaſure. They are full of Children, and leave the reſt of their Subſtance to their Babes,</hi> Pſal. 17. 10, 14. <hi>Then ſaid Jeſus unto his Diſciples, Verily, I ſay unto you, that a Rich Man ſhall hardly enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. And again I ſay unto you, It is eaſier for a Camel to go through the eye of a Needle, then for a Rich Man to enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> Mat. 19, 23, 24. <hi>Therefore ſhall the Lord of Hoſts, ſend among his fat ones leanneſs—Behold the Lord of Hoſts, ſhall lop the Bough with Terrour, and the High ones of Stature ſhall be hewn down, and the Haughty ſhall be Humbled,</hi> Iſa. 10.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151376:4"/> 16, 33. <hi>The Lord of Hoſts hath Purpoſed it, to Stain the Pride of all Glory, and to bring into contempt all the Honourable of the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 23. 9. <hi>How much ſhe hath Glorifyed her ſelf, and lived deliciouſly, ſo much Torment and Sorrow give her, Rev. 18, 7. The Lord God hath Sworn by himſelf, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts, I abhor the Excellency of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and hate his Palaces,</hi> Amos. 6, 1. Here God (whoſe thoughts are not your thoughts <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55, 8. declares his <hi>abhorrence</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> againſt them, whom the World Loves and Reſpects, Flatters and endeavours to pleaſe. <hi>Surely Men of Low degree are Vanity, and Men of High degree are a lie,</hi> Pſal. 62, 9. Obſerve here that Blunt expreſſion, and plain Engliſh (if we may ſo ſay) of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Men of High degree are a lie.</hi> Which ſeems to intimate forth, that that opinion or Eſtimation, which other People have of them, or they of themſelves, as if there were ſome what in them, which were more, above, or better then other Men, is a meer <hi>lie</hi> and Falſhood. <hi>Yet now our Fleſh</hi> (ſpeaking of thoſe in Debt and Poverty) <hi>is as the Fleſh of our Brethren,</hi> (who were more Rich and Wealthy) <hi>our Children as their Children</hi> Neh. 5, 5. <hi>God hath made of one Blood all Nations of Men,</hi> Acts. 17, 26. Which includes High and Low, Rich and Poor alike. So it is in God's account now, and as to the future Judgment he will make concerning them. <hi>Will he eſteem thy Riches, no not thy Gold, nor all the forces of Strength,</hi> Job. 36, 19. <hi>That accepteth not the Perſons of Princes, nor regardeth the Rich more then the Poor, for they are all the Work of his Hands,</hi> Job, 34, 19. O that there were the ſame <hi>God-like</hi> mind in my kindred according to the Fleſh; for as to them and ſome others, this following Scripture is Literally fulfilled in me, <hi>Our So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exceedingly filled with the Scorning of thoſe that are at Eaſe, and with the contempt of the Proud,</hi> Pſal 123. 4. Indeed it is fit and Requiſite, that there ſhould be ſome order and Diſtinction amongſt Men and Women in the World; but then on the other hand, for any one whatever, to have hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heart lifted up above his Brethren,</hi> Deut. 17, 20. Or to <hi>deſpiſe the Poor,</hi> James, 2, 6. is a Sinful and Wrong extream</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord ſeeth not as Man ſeeth, For Man looketh on the outward Appearance, but the Lord looketh on the Heart,</hi> 1 Sam 16, 7. If there be Beauty or Gayety without, Man hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wonderful conceit of him, as of ſome goodly one; but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Heart (which is as manifeſt in God's Sight, as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Face is in ours) be evil, notwithſtanding the fine outſide
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151376:4"/> ſuch an one is as much <hi>hated</hi> and <hi>abhorred</hi> (It is his own Phraſe in <hi>Amos</hi> 6, 8.) in God's Sight, as the moſt abject and contemptible Fellow is in ours. <hi>For thou wilt ſave the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted People, but wilt bring down High looks,</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l, 18, 27. In the former Part of this Verſe is Favour and Mercy to the Poor and <hi>Afflicted,</hi> but in the latter part thereof, is Terrour and Evil to the Rich and High minded. God's thoughts are contrary to Mans thoughts; for he ſpeaks in favour and comfort of the Poor, whom the World abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and deſpiſeth. On the other hand, he ſpeaks Terrour, and to <hi>Humble</hi> thoſe (as may be ſeen in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 33. afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted) who are ſo much flattered and whoſe <hi>Perſons are had in Admiration becauſe of advantage,</hi> Jude 16. The ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy of all which they ſhall feel, who do not mind theſe things, nor take due warning. The Scripture runs thus all a long, when it mentions that difference of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward State and Condition, of Poor and Rich, promiſing good things to the former ſort, and denouncing evil things to the latter ſort. <hi>And</hi> Abraham <hi>ſaid to the Rich Man, Son, Remember that thou in thy Life Time Receivedſt thy Good things, and likewiſe</hi> Lazarus <hi>Evil Things, but now he is Comforted, and thou art Tormented,</hi> Luke 16, 25.</p>
            <p>Now to make known how I did apply all this to my ſelf, which the Reader may apply to himſelf alſo; for in the application and bringing it home to our ſelves, there is the Uſe and Godly Edification. I ſay, that Conſidering all theſe things together, and weighing them in my mind; For I do believe, and am perſwaded, that it is as certainly true, and will be ſo in the <hi>times of the Reſtitution of all things,</hi> as, now I am ſure that I write theſe lines; hereupon God knows that I Lie not, I did wiſh and deſire, that I my ſelf might be brought into the condition of the Poor and Needy, to the intent that I might come in for a ſhare, and to be a partaker of thoſe Precious Promiſes, which throughout the Scripture God hath made unto them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>As God commanded <hi>Hoſea</hi> to take a <hi>Wife of Whoredoms,</hi> ſo I was directed, and for which ſame Reaſon alſo I did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>viz.</hi> On the ſeventh Day of the ſeventh Month, 1694. Marry a Maiden, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. 22. as Poor in outward State and Condition, as Poor well could be; for ſhe and her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were in the very next degree, to open and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Beggary. But I made choice of ſuch an one the rather, Thinking that hereby I might make more ſure of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151376:5"/> Partaking of thoſe Precious Promiſes afore-mentioned and that hereby I ſhould obtain a better Reſurrection in the future State of things.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Marvel not at this; for it is ſomewhat like that <hi>Mind which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3. 5. <hi>Who though h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was Rich, yet for our ſakes he became Poor, that we through his Poverty might be Rich,</hi> And ſo though I was in a Moderate Condition, yet I Voluntarily (of mine own free choice, and not out of any Imprudent Management) <hi>became Poor</hi> for the Goſpel's ſake, and for the better making known the <hi>Truth as it is in Jeſus.</hi> The like may any one elſe do, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it be in <hi>good Works,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 18, 19. and in Acts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Alms giving <hi>to their Power, yea and beyond their Power,</hi> 2 Cor. 8. 3. but not in Pride or Pleaſure, Prodigality o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Vain Things, or in what is Sin, Fooliſh or Unlawful; for ſuch who <hi>become Poor</hi> any of theſe ways will not receive any thing from the Lord, but Wrath and Puniſhment,</p>
            <p>But my firſt Wiſh and Deſire of this Nature, was ſome Conſiderable time before I had ever known. what Want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Need was in all my foregoing Life, which I have Experienc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince, and may yet again. I did not then know nor in the leaſt apprehend, how or after what manner, or by what I ſhould be involved, into Poverty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which God hath Since ſhewed to me, That is to ſay <hi>By Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of, and Suffering for God's Eternal Truth</hi> (which is the <hi>beſt of Works)</hi> and by the <hi>oppreſſion of Man,</hi> Pfal. 119, 134 which hath aroſe upon that occaſion. Although this ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truth hath occaſioned to me Poverty, Impriſonments 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. Trouble and Sorrow, <hi>But I will Hope conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually and Praiſe thee yet more and more.</hi> For I believe ſtill tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at Length it will have the Contrary Good Effects, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſhall yet Praiſe thee upon the Pſaltery, even thy Truth, O m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God.</hi> Pſal. 71. 14, 21. Which will be, if either I ſhould live on this Earth to ſee it Obeyed. For there is an Obedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nevertheleſs due to the Truth, as may be gathered from <hi>Rom. 2, 8. Gal.</hi> 3, 1. although in both thoſe places Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obey it not. Or rather it will be when my Work ſhall be Rewarded, in the time of the Reſtitution of all Things for my bringing it forth, and for my Suffering for it.</p>
            <p>I Do hereby take this occaſion and opportunity, to Praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and to declare his Wonders <hi>(for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am as a Wonder unto many,</hi> Pſal. 71, 7.) Even to thank and Exalt his Holy Name for Granting my deſire in this thing;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151376:5"/> for it Springs into my Soul, as ſome Comfortable Evidence (though Strangers, and Natural People cannot preceive and <hi>diſcern</hi> it) that I am indeed an Heir of Salvation, in that I have lived by his Grace and good Providence here on Earth, and was in the ſame <hi>Low Eſtate,</hi> Pſal: 136, 23. For the ſame and like Reaſons, as his Elect, and Servants of former Generations. Whoſe are the Promiſes of better things, then thoſe which pertain to the Life that now is, even to that which is to come. <hi>According as his Divine Power hath given unto us, all Things that pertain to Life and Godlineſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 3. Although the former Sort were Poor, Low and Mean, yet they were Sufficient to that End: According as his Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs thought expedient. <hi>Bleſs the Lord O my Soul, and all that is within me Bleſs his Holy Name. Bleſs the Lord O my Soul, and forget not all his benefits; which</hi> aforemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I eſteem and receive as ſuch: Although <hi>the Natural Man diſcerns it not,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 14. The Ignorant Perſon and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever do not apprehend any in it, but they call it my Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune Ruine and Miſery. <hi>But I know whom I have believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and I lay hold on that Promiſe, <hi>They ſhall not be Aſhamed that Wait for me,</hi> Iſa. 49. 23. And although in this preſent life, where neither the <hi>Judgment written,</hi> Pſ. 149. 9. is Executed, nor yet the Reward promiſed is Actually given, many of the Servants of God, have been Liable to ſhame and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the World; Yet the anſwer of God, ſaith unto them on this Wiſe, for further Hope and Encouragement, <hi>But Iſrael ſhall be Saved in the Lord, with an Everlaſting Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Ye ſhall not be aſhamed, nor Confounded World without End,</hi> Iſa. 45, 17. At long Run, it ſhall not be thus; but in the End of Time, all things that are written in the Scriptures, ſhall be fulfilled and found True.</p>
            <p>As alſo hereby I have been taught and experienced with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the Text: (One calls the School of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions the beſt School; and the wiſdom of God ſaith as to this, <hi>It is good for a Man that he bear his Yoke in his Youth,</hi> Lam. 3. 27.) <hi>I know both how to be abaſed, and I know how to abound every where and in all things, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need. I can do all things through Christ which ſtrengtheneth me.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151376:6"/>
            <p>And becauſe of what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>For there is nothing hid which ſhall not be manifeſted, neither was any thing kept ſecret but that it ſhould come abroad,</hi> Mark 4. 32. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from this being the mind of Chriſt, I think it both proper and convenient to declare and make known, what condition, I one of his Miniſters and Members have been brought into, as I was in the Miniſtration of his word and ſuffering for the ſame. I being once in great Anguiſh of Spirit with Tears in mine Eyes, like <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>When the Water was ſpent in the Bottle,</hi> Gen. 21. 15. Being at a conſiderable diſtance from my Native Country, when almoſt all my Money was gone, and I did not know where to have more, and then I had moſt need of it; I thereupon fell down upon my knees to God. And there I <hi>Poured out my complaint before him and ſhewed him my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> And as it is commanded and directed in the Goſpel, <hi>Be careful for nothing, but in every thing with Prayer and Supplication, with Thanſgiving let your requeſts be made known unto God,</hi> Phil. 46. Accordingly I did then make known my Requeſts unto him, and then within leſs than a quarter of an hour, I perceived a ſtill Voice ſpeaking to my Soul on this wiſe, <hi>Thou haſt made known thy Requeſts unto God, go forth and do the ſame unto his Servants.</hi> This was one of the moſt ſenſible Anſwers, and Return to Prayer that ever I perceived and obſerved in all my Life-time, and was ſomewhat like that which we read in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 21, 22, 23. And thereupon I went forth the day following, and made known my Requeſts unto them, and asked for the Alms and willing Contribution of Chriſtian People; and of the two firſt which I ever made application unto, I had rather a matter of Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nty and Liberality, than a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Alms-giving, being received by them with a great deal of courteouſneſs and civility. And from thenceforth for well nigh two years and an half <hi>(Bleſſed be the Lord, for he hath ſhewed me his kindneſs in a ſtrong and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous City)</hi> I ſubſiſted, and was fed by a wonderful and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued train and courſe of Providence, according to that uſual method thereof <hi>He that had gathered much, had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over; and he that had gathered little, had no lack, 2 Cor.</hi> 8. 15. It being agreeable with the wiſdom and ways of God, to do nothing which is ſuperfluous, or more than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151376:6"/> needs muſt; nor yet is he wanting in what means are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary: And ſo I had juſt ſufficient for my ſeveral needs, and not much more nor yet leſs; and it was reached forth unto me by the viſible hand of Inviſible Providence juſt at the time, or a little before as I had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. Herein I found that Scripture litterally fulfilled in me, <hi>When my Father and my Mother forſake me, then the Lord will take me up, Pſal.</hi> 27. 10. The Holy Spirit by ſpeaking after that manner, doth preſuppoſe that the Servants of God may be reduced to ſuch kind of ſtraits and exigencies, for the Scripture ſaith <hi>nothing in vain.</hi> And ſo when my Father and Mother-in-Law did forſake me and with-hold Maintenance, then the Lord did take me up and provide for me by the good will and miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Servants, Bleſſed be his Name for it. Thus in this Poor, Low, Beggarly (that is, a condition of asking) Eſtate, I have learned to be content, and in all things I have been inſtructed both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer want. By the way it is better, and rather to be choſen to be a Beggar, than to be unjuſt or unrighteous, for we read of one Beggar, namely <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> who went to Heaven, but the Scripture ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>Know ye not that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God, 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 9. Yea, of what was extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards me by way of Alms I had a ſweet reliſh and enjoyment thereof, becauſe I did Eye the goodneſs of God in and through it: And hereby a proof and trial was had of Peoples ſubjection and obedience to the commands of the Goſpel. Said the Author thereof, Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>The Poor are ſuffered to be with you always, that whenſoever you will, you may do them good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth thus write in his own Perſon unto the <hi>Phillippians,</hi> as in our Text, and ſo he doth in many other places of his Epiſtles, ſo it doth in no wiſe derogate or vary from the Gravity, Seriouſneſs, or Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſound Preaching or Writing, for the Miniſter to declare his own Experiences unto the Hearers; for they, by comparing theirs with the ſame, may be Profited and Edified hereby. That according to what is written, It may be the ſame with them alſo, <hi>Thoſe things which ye have both Learned and Received, and heard and ſeen in me,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151376:7"/> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Phillippians) do, and the God of Peace ſhall be with you,</hi> Phil. 4. 9.</p>
            <p>It is an eaſy matter to be content with a Plentiful, Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous and Abounding State; but here is the Virtue and the Praiſe, if People can be and are content with, as that amidſt and under theſe Evil things, they will not charge God fooliſhly, nor ſuffer their hearts to fret againſt him; nor yet will they ſin, nor put forth their hands to Iniquity. Altho' thereby they might be delivered and freed from them.</p>
            <p>Contentment doth denote an even and ſmooth temper of mind, a Calmneſs and Tranquillity of Spirit, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to thoſe liftings up and caſtings down, or when it is like the <hi>troubled Sea and cannot reſt.</hi> Again, It is Peace and not Stupidity or Ignorance. It rubs and goes on through this Earth, and doth not lye ſtill in ſloth and deadneſs. I mean, when a Man knows throughly the Nature of things and therewith is content; but he is ſomewhat beyond the blockiſhneſs and ſence of a Beaſt; which is content with its condition, becauſe it knows nothing better. As alſo the Soul, tho' it is content with what outward things ſhe hath, is not therefore Idle or Unprofitable, but travels and makes towards the Father of Spirits. A certain Heathen Poet hath deſcribed it on this wiſe, <hi>That ſhe is almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the preſent, but yet doth attempt and try after greater things.</hi> And indeed, if we confine our ſelves only to ſuch things which are Juſt, Lawful and Right, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is both the Duty, and alſo very conſiſtent with a Servant of the Lord; To be up and be doing, and ſo far endeavouring after them, as they do not hinder from bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more Precious things. This alſo comes within that Aphoriſm, or Rule of the ſame Apoſtle, through whom the Spirit of God hath made known the Words of our Text, <hi>Art thou called being a Servant? Care not for it, but if thou mayeſt be made free, uſe it rather,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 21.</p>
            <p>Thus having in ſome meaſure explained the Nature of Chriſtian Contentment, or at leaſt ſo far hinted and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated concerning it; That the Reader may gather and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the reſidue thereof, Proceed we now to lay down ſome Arguments and Reaſons to enforce the obſervance thereof, or to beget the ſame mind in ye alſo, as afore is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151376:7"/> ſaid. Thoſe things which ye have both learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and heard and ſeen in his Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> do, and the <hi>God of Peace,</hi> (under which word Contentment is includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt and greateſt Argument for Contentment or Contentation, to me ſeems to be, in knowing and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering throughly our own Creature ſtate; and that the will of God doth Order and Over-rule all things in this World. This Conſideration is two fold. It would be proper therefore to ſpeak ſomewhat of them ſeverally, and then connect and joyn them together, and then ſhew what influence and efficacy this double Conſideration hath to make us hold our Peace; <hi>Submit our ſelves to God, James</hi> 4. 7. and to learn <hi>in whatſoever ſtate we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Firſt place, O Man, know thine own <hi>Creature State,</hi> how thou wert at firſt made by God, and how that now thou art a Creature in his hands, and purely at his Government, Rule, and Diſpoſal. One would think, this were the eaſieſt thing in the World to be underſtood, but yet it remains a Myſtery, and doth puzzle the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of People; for even unto this day, <hi>when Moſes</hi> or the Prophets, or the Goſpel is read, <hi>the veil is upon their hearts;</hi> and an Inviſible God is an Unknown God to the multitude and generality of Mankind, in what is called this Chriſtian Nation. For either becauſe they ſee not God, or rather they do forget him. Thence it is that they do not <hi>look unto the Rock from whence they were hewn nor have Reſpect unto the hole from whence they were digged;</hi> even ſo as to eye continually, and <hi>have reſpect,</hi> Which ſignifies looking back <hi>unto their Maker,</hi> and ſo as to ſee him that is inviſible; <hi>Which holdeth our Soul in Life, and ſuffereth not our feet to be moved, Pſal.</hi> 66. 9. In the Margent there it is putteth, which doth relate to the initial Act of our Creation, as the Word <hi>holdeth</hi> doth denote the continuance thereof all the while we are in Life. Both which are very proper and ſignificative of what our Inviſible Maker and Creator doth unto us. For indeed he doth firſt put our Soul in Life, and then holdeth it therein, all the days which on this Earth it is in the Body. Like as when <hi>Elijah</hi> raiſed the dead Child,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151376:8"/> he cried unto the Lord, and ſaid, <hi>O Lord, my God, I pray thee, let this Childs Soul come into him again,</hi> 1 Kings 4. 6. By comparing of all which together, we come to know the truth and the manner of our being in this Life, more than ever any Heathen could attain unto by meer reaſon, by having it thus revealed unto us, how that God at firſt putteth, and then holdeth, and at length cauſes the Soul to depart from this Body; and in the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he will let our Souls come into our Bodies again. In the aforeſaid place of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 9. it is added, <hi>And ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not our feet to be moved.</hi> Now the feet are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of our moving to and fro; ſo that we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from hence that all our Actions or Motions are orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God according to what the Scripture elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſaith plainly, in divers places, <hi>Mans goings are of the Lord, How can a man then underſtand his own way, Prov. 20. O Lord, I know that the way of a Man is not in himſelf; it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps,</hi> Jer. 10. 23. <hi>The ſteps of a good Man are ordered by the Lord, and he delighteth in his way,</hi> Pſal. 37. 23. Here it is expreſſed by goings and ſteps, which take in all, and extend even to the very leaſt Motions of his; for ſo are ſteps, and ſo it is as to all of them particularly and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally. But by that Phraſe of <hi>Jeremiah, O Lord, I know,</hi> is imported forth that his Saints and Servants do live in a continued ſenſe and knowledge of as much; which bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Men, and Ignorant Perſons, and Unbelievers do not. For the Truth is, <hi>As in him we live, move, and have our Being,</hi> ſo our ſeveral Actions and Doings are ordered of the Lord, though too many do not ſee and diſcern it. <hi>Thou broughteſt us into the Net, thou laidſt Affliction up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Loins, Pſal.</hi> 66. 11. I have much thought of this Scripture, when I have been for the Word and Truth of God caſt into Priſon, where was croſs-barrs of Iron, and Wood, which did exactly reſemble a Net. Here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Carnal and Ignorant Perſons, and Unbelievers, will ſay and reply, That ſuch brought themſelves into Trouble and Afflictions, and they think nothing of God herein. But here again, Let <hi>God be true, and themſelves Liars; that thou mighteſt be juſtified in thy Saying, and overcom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (the Imaginations and Talk of People) <hi>when thou judgest.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151376:8"/> For <hi>David</hi> here ſaith thus by the Spirit, and aſcribes it up immediately to God himſelf; <hi>Thou broughteſt us into the Net, thou laidſt Affliction upon our Loins.</hi> For indeed he doth herein ſpeak as one that had a through Knowledge and Underſtanding of, and inſight into this Matter.</p>
            <p>And it may be conceived after this manner; the ſame <hi>Lord who ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth on his Throne, and all the Hoaſt of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (who alſo Order and Diſpoſe of Things here on Earth) <hi>ſtood by him on his Right and on his left. And the Lord ſaid, Who ſhall go and perſwade Ahab that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-Gilead? And one ſaid on this manner, and another ſaid on that manner. And there came forth a Spirit, and ſtood before the Lord, and ſaid, I will perſwade him. And the Lord ſaid unto him, wherewith? And he ſaid, I will go forth, and I will be a Lying Spirit in the mouth of all his Prophets. And he ſaid, Thou ſhalt perſwade him, and prevail alſo; go forth, and do ſo; 1 Kings</hi> 22. 19, 20, 28. Why after the ſame ſimilitude of things, yea after the very ſame manner doth the Lord, <hi>who looketh from Heaven, he beholdeth all the Sons of Men from the place of his Habitation, He looketh upon all the Inhabitants of the Earth, he faſhioneth their hearts alike, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth all their Works,</hi> Pſal. 33. 14, 15. And ſo he doth Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Over-rule, and diſpoſe of all their ways and Works. For thus much may be underſtood; that he our God, or an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Spirit from the Lord acts in every Man and Woman by Thoughts or Imaginations. By Thoughts I mean ſuch as are true and good. By Imaginations I intend ſuch as are falſe or evil. And theſe Thoughts or Imaginations are the immediate Fore-runners, Principles, or Cauſes of Action. But here take heed how thou affirmeſt too far, <hi>for let no Man ſay when he is tempted, I am tempted of God; for God cannot be tempted with Evil, neither tempteth he any Man,</hi> James, 1. 13. So do not thou ſay, that God acts in Man or Woman by falſe or evil Imaginations, for God cannot be the Author of Falſhood or Evil; neither doth he tempt or act any Man to it. All this is true, but yet this difficulty may be well underſtood and reconciled from the aforecited, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22: for there it is ſaid, <hi>All the Hoſt of Heaven ſtood before him on his right Hand, and on his left.</hi> So that there were good and true Spirits which probably ſtood on his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151376:9"/> right Hand; and evil and falſe Spirits which ſtood on his left Hand. But as an Earthly King doth this or that thing by his Miniſters or Officers, ſo the Everlaſting God, the Creator of the Ends of the Earth, whom the Scripture ſtiles a <hi>great King,</hi> (as ſo indeed he is) doth act and work through and by his created Beings; that is, by his Angels or Spirits. He ſends forth and commands his good Angels or Spirits. He permits or ſuffers the evil Angels or Spirits. And one of theſe two ſorts doth actuate, or Act in all the Children of Men, according as we read of the <hi>Prince of the Power of the Air, the Spirit that now worketh in the Children of Diſobedience.</hi> True it is, <hi>Thou art of purer Eyes than to behold Evil, and canſt not look on Iniquity, Hab.</hi> 1. 13. Nor yet is he the Efficient Cauſe or Author of ſin or Evil. But yet as <hi>He giveth to all Life and Breath, and all things, Acts</hi> 17. 25. And he hath Created all things, and for thy Pleaſure they are and were Created, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. 11. And ſo he doth uphold and govern all things, that they cannot move or act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; Therefore of neceſſity he muſt be ſo far concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſin or evil (for he ſuffers that, as he did the <hi>manners of the Iſraelites Fourty Years in the Wilderneſs)</hi> as is before explained. For though it hath been a puzzling thing unto Divines to aſſign, how that nothing hath been, nor yet can be done in the World, but what is the Will of God that the ſame ſhould have been done, for otherwiſe it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible and had never been done, and yet in all this, to keep his Holineſs unſtained from the Sin or Evil; That he is not in the leaſt a Partaker with and ſharer thereof, and that the Will of God is Holy, and Juſt, and Good; but too many things have been done on this Earth which are Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, Unjuſt and Evil. But yet by <hi>Aſcribing Greatneſs unto our God,</hi> how he at firſt made and containeth all things, <hi>By lifting up our Eyes on high, and beholding who hath creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all theſe things, that bringeth out their Hoſt by Number, he calleth them all by their Names, by the Greatneſs of his might, for that he is ſtrong in Power, not one faileth:</hi> By knowing how that he is Sovereign and Infinitely above all other things. By knowing how that the ſame God, <hi>Who made Man at firſt upright, but he ſought out many Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> So in the very beginning he made the Devil and all his Legions of Spirits Good Creatures at firſt, for that is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151376:9"/> made upon the ſeveral parts of the Creation. <hi>And God ſaw that it was Good.</hi> But the Devil and his Angels became Evil of themſelves, and <hi>ſinned, 2 Pet. 2. 4. and kept not their firſt Eſtate, Jude</hi> 6. And now they are the Black Fountain beneath, from whence do ſpring up all Sin or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. But God (who now ſuffers it all, and over-rules it for the <hi>Great Ends</hi> of his Glory) is high, and as much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted above it all, as the Sun in the Firmament ſhining in its brightneſs, is above a Quagmire, Dunghill, or dark hole of the Earth. For all the Sin or Evil which hath been, now is, or ſhall ever be, doth no more Impair, Leſſen, or Darken his Holineſs, then the other now doth, as to the bright Beams of the Sun. Take and conſider all this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into our underſtandings, with the other Divine Truths which relate to this matter, and they do all moſt clearly open and unfold this myſtery, How God doth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſin and yet is not the Author thereof; and how all things both Animate and Inanimate do his will; and yet Nevertheleſs His Will, like his Commandment, <hi>Is Holy, Juſt and Good.</hi> So that though the Committing of Sin is not according to the will of God in which he is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; yet it is the will of God barely to ſuffer, and then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to Puniſh it. For Notwithſtanding all that is here ſaid, ſtill there is a fault, Evil deſerving and willfulneſs in the reaſonable Creature, in Committing Sin or Evil, or in ſpeaking Falſhood; &amp; upon that fault &amp; evil deſerving of theirs, the future Puniſhment of God is righteouſly founded.</p>
            <p>Here we ſhould remember our Creature State, How that Angels and Devils, Men and Beaſts, Birds and Fiſhes, Things with life or without life, viſible or inviſible, they are all but Creatures, or Inſtruments in the Hands of God, for to do whatever his hand or his Counſel hath determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or ſuffered to be done. <hi>For of a Truth againſt thy Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Child Jeſus, whom thou haſt anointed, both</hi> Herod <hi>and</hi> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate <hi>with the Gentiles, and the People of</hi> Iſrael <hi>were gathered together, for to do whatſoever thy Hand and thy Counſel determined before to be done,</hi> Act. 4. 27 28. In like manner it may be reaſoned and applied of the whoſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, <hi>Fire and Hail, Snow and Vapour, ſtormy Wind fulfilling his Word,</hi> Pſal. 148. 8. So all the living Creatures in all their Actings and Movings, do agree and meet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for to do <hi>Whatſoever thy Hand and thy Counſel determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before to be done.</hi> So the Devil and his Legions, and all thoſe People in the fleſh, our Fellow-creatures, they are all but Inſtruments in the Hands of God (for the Devil
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151376:10"/> Acted through <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> in putting Chriſt to Death) for to do <hi>Whatſoever thy Hand and thy Counſel determined before to be done.</hi> And ſo all thoſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, Trials and Temptations, are to be looked upon, which do befall any of the Children of Men. <hi>David</hi> could ſay concerning <hi>Shimei, Let him alone, let him Curſe, for the Lord hath bidden him,</hi> 2 Sam. 6. 11. <hi>Abiſha</hi> did call him a <hi>dead Dog</hi> for thus doing. And here we may make uſe of this Parallel and Similitude, we ſhould not be like unto Ignorant and Angry Dogs to bite the ſtone, without hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpect unto him that flings it. So alas! We are too apt to blame, and to have indignation at that Fellow-crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ours, or outward Accident, whom, or which we ſuppoſe to be the cauſe of our Affliction, Loſs, or Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. But here we ſhould rather be ſilent and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, take it with the Spirit of meekneſs and willing reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for the <hi>Lord hath bidden him,</hi> or he hath given Commiſſion and Leave to ſuch an Evil or Lying Spirit, to Act through Incarnate or viſible Inſtruments ſuch afflicting things againſt us. As in good things, It is not ſuch a Man, but <hi>Chriſt who dwelleth in him,</hi> doth the ſame, ſo in evil things the Devil Acts through ſuch who do evil. And over and above all things, we may look up to the Great Inviſible God, who Over-rules and Determines all for the Great Ends of his own Glory. <hi>Who will make all things work together for Good, to them that love God, to them who are the called ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Purpoſe,</hi> Rom. 8. 28.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of all this put together ſhould make us to lay our hand upon our mouth, to have a care leaſt we reply againſt God. <hi>Shall the thing formed ſay unto him that forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, why haſt thou made me thus?</hi> Shall the Creature Governed by him and dependant on him, ſay, Why haſt thou ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ordered it to be thus or thus with me, which I do not like, or I had rather it was otherwiſe. <hi>Hath not the Potter Power over the clay of the ſame lump, to make ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Veſſel to Honour and another to Diſhonour?</hi> Is it not Lawful for the Good Man of the Houſe, for the Lord and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the World, <hi>To do what he will with his own? Sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we receive Good at the Hands of God, and ſhall we not receiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Evil? The Lord gave and the Lord hath taken away; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Name of the Lord. For the Lord will not caſt off for ever; But though He cauſe grief, yet will He have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion according to the Multitude of his mercies; for He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the Children of Men,</hi> Lam. 3. 31, 32, 33. Theſe and ſuch like things are written
<pb facs="tcp:151376:10"/> and ſcattered up and down here and there in the Book of the Lord for our Comfort and Contentment. <hi>Be ſtill and know that I am God.</hi> That he is our Creator, and we are pure and meer Creatures in his hands. We may perceive a manifeſt diverſity between his own Omnipotency, or Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightineſs (if I may ſo expreſs it) and our own impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, inability and weakneſs. For it is evident and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, that there are many things which we would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave, and yet we cannot obtain, which we endeavour after, and yet cannot accompliſh. As our Bodily motion is confined to ſuch a degree, beyond which we cannot move faſter: Our ſtrength is alſo limited to ſuch a Pitch, that we can lift ſo much and no more. So we may perceive as to all our other Powers of Action, that they are determined and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited on every ſide. There is none who in this mortal and imperfect ſtate hath all his deſires, or every thing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his mind, even as he would have. God is to be eyed and obſerved in this thing alſo, and it is meet to be ſaid unto him, <hi>It is the Lord, let him do with me what ſeemeth him Good.</hi> It was a Good Reſigned and Contented Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Diſpoſition of <hi>David,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>If I ſhall find favour in the Eyes of the Lord, He will bring me up again, and ſhew me both it</hi> (the Ark) <hi>and his Habitation. But if He thus ſay, I have no delight in thee, behold here am I, let him do to me as ſeemeth Good unto him,</hi> 2 Sam. 15. 25, 26. Even ſo in all the difficulties and doubts of our Life, amidſt all fears and troubles, we ſhould refer them all unto God. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord,</hi> (the Marginal read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng is, Roll thy way upon the Lord) <hi>truſt alſo in him and he ſhall bring it to paſs: Reſt in the Lord and wait patiently for him,</hi> Pſal. 37. 5, 7. And under the Goſpel it is commanded, <hi>Caſting all your care upon him, for He careth for you,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thou ſhalt remember all the way which the Lord thy God led thee in the Wilderneſs; where thou haſt ſeen how, that as a Man bareth his Son, ſo did the Lord bare thee in all the way that thou wenteſt,</hi> This expreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt ſeems to allude unto a Man carrying a Suckling, or Infant in his Arms, which cannot go of it ſelf, but muſt go whither it is carried, and it knows not. Even ſo we are as B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bes and Sucklings unto God; And he doth ſo carry us his Creatures in this Life and through this Wilderneſs of the Earth, tho' too many do not ſee, know and diſcern as much. <hi>For the Lords Portion is his People,</hi> Jacob <hi>is the Lot of his I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance. He led him about, He inſtructed him, He kept him as the Apple of his Eye. As an Eagle ſtirreth up her Neſt, flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth
<pb facs="tcp:151376:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151376:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151376:12"/> over her Young, ſprea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h abroad her Wings, taketh them and beareth them on her Wings.</hi> (Behold, what a fit Compariſon here is to reſemble and ſet forth, how the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Creator doth brood over his viſible Creatures and take care of them: Like as we read of in the beginning, <hi>And the Spirit of God, mooved upon the Face of the Waters,</hi> Gen. 1. 2. Even ſo ever ſince his Spirit, yea, his own Being and Himſelf doth Encompaſs and contain and over-ſhadow the Face of all his Creation, <hi>He upholding all things by the Word of his Power) ſo the Lord alone did lead him, and there was no ſtrange God in him. He made him ride on the High Places of the Earth, that he might eat the Increaſe of the Fields, and He made him to ſuck Honey out of the Rock<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Oyl out of the flinty Rock. Butter of Kine, and Milk of Sheep, with fat of Lambs, and Rams, of the Breed</hi> Baſhan; <hi>and Goats, with the fat of Kidneys, of Wheat, and thou didſt drink the Pure Blood of the Grape,</hi> Deut. 32. 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. From all which we may ſee, that even the leaſt things pertaining to Life and to the Body (the husk and ſhell of the Soul) are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by God our Maker, and then much more doth he take care and diſpoſe of things for that, even the better and more enduring ſubſtance within us.</p>
            <p>I have often thought as to the ſeveral Paſſages, Occurrences, and Things which I meet withal in the courſe of mine own Life, both as to what is paſt or preſent, ſome of which I do remember, but what is to come God only knows; That as when <hi>Peter was let out of Priſon by the Angel who bid him follow me, when they were past the firſt and ſecond Ward, they came unto the Iron Gate that le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deth unto the City, which opened to them of his own accord,</hi> Acts 12. 10. From that laſt, I have thus ſeveral times concluded and reaſoned within m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, that if ſuch, or ſuch a thing which I have a deſire or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting after, were indeed the mind or will of God, that it ſhould be done for me or had by me; why then, as <hi>Peter</hi> did follow the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, ſo if I did uſe the common means and endeavours after it, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch means as are true and prudent, lawful and right and no others, as after they had paſt the firſt and ſecond ward, the Iron Gate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to them of his own accord. So altho' there may be ſome mean difficulty and oppoſition, which may be rubbed over and got through, yet at length away would open of its own accord, to Perfect and Conſummate the ſame thing, That we may actually and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed obtain it, or arrive at the place where we would be. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no I have gueſſed at, or rather found out the very Truth as it ſtands in the Nature and Connexion of things, the Lord knows. <hi>But I proteſt by your rejoycing, which I have in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord;</hi> I Proteſt, by my Trouble and Vexation of Spirit, which I have ſometimes about wordly and outward things, this ſame is a mighty Word of Conſolation and Contentment unto me, in the ſeveral Expectations which I have framed and raiſed to my ſelf, and in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151376:12"/> ſeveral Diſappointments which I have met withal throughout this life, centring ſtill upon this Foundation and Point, <hi>The Will of the Lord be done,</hi> and let me willingly ſubmit unto that ſame his will, whatever it is or ſhall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe things I have ſpoken unto you, that in me ye might have Peace, in the World ye ſhall have Tribulation, but be of Good Cheer, I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome the World,</hi> John 16. 33. Is not this very ſame thing felt and experienced at this Day? For doth not all the Tribulation, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Vexation ariſe from the World and from the things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? It is ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> very deed with me as I think off, and am buſied in the things and concernments thereof, but when again, I lift up my heart above all the thoughts thereof, then it becomes Calm and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Smooth and Clear, as the upper Region of the Air, which is above all Winds, Storms, Tempeſts, or Clouds. For the Knowledge of God and the great things of Eternity, doth ſwallow up, darken and obſcure all the little things of this lower World, as the Sun ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its Brightneſs at Mid-day, doth make, ſo that we do not then perceive any Light of Moon or Stars, albeit they are then equally fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Firmament, and give their faintlight all one as at night time</p>
            <p>There is no ſuch help in the World towards Contentment, as to have the Knowledge of God; Eſpecially to know and conceive of him as hath been juſt now explained. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that ſome of the Chriſtians dwelling at <hi>Corinth</hi> to whom he Writes, <hi>Had not the Knowledge of God, I ſpeak this to your ſhame,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 34. As truly it is to the ſhame of all who Name, or profeſs the Name of Chriſt to be found without it. But it muſt be ſuppoſed, yea, It is moſt certain and evident, that <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf had the Knowledge of God. For otherwiſe, as he could never have wrote ſo many true and excellent things concerning God. And it was by this Knowledge of God (even, as he is the Creator, Governour and Diſpoſer of all things) that he had thereby <hi>Learned in whatſoever State he was therewith to be content. I know both how to be abaſed, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow how to abound,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By what hath been aforeſaid, this Leſſon may be ſomewhat Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in whatſoever State, Thou O Man, art in, therewith to be Content. And that ye may come to this Knowledge, both to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed and how to abound, Be ſure to take in the Knowledge of God and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and then this Leſſon is eaſily Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as alſo the other Knowledge will be ſoon attained unto. <hi>But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> So here it is, in the firſt place, know God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as He, or they are to be Known; and then all the other will fall in of Courſe. For then according to the Words of our Text, <hi>Every where, and in all things, ye will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrusted both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to ſuffer need.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no need to uſe many more Words, to ſhew and inculcate the ſame. But as it is Written, <hi>And this is Life Eternal, that they might know thee, the only true God and Jeſus Christ whom thou haſt ſent:</hi> Even ſo this is the Sweetneſs and Comfort, the Peace and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, the Quiet and Smoothneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151376:13"/> neſs of this preſent Temporal Life. To know thee, the only true God (as He is Supreme Lord, Governour and Diſpoſer of all things) and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, the Eternal Word, whereby God is more ſeen and manifeſt unto our Souls. Alas! when we are amidſt trouble, Vexation and Reſtleſsneſs of Spirit, it is moſt commonly becauſe we forget God, and behave our ſelves falſly in his Covenant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But did we know and ſee him with the Eyes of our Underſtanding being enlightened? Were our Hearts pure and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right before him? How ſweetly and contentedly might we live, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Apprehenſion and Care, and Protection of this Good God above; All one, yea, and much more then Subjects under a Lawful and Excellent Prince, Children under a Loving and Good, a Juſt and Wiſe Father; and as Servants under the beſt of Maſters. For God doth approve himſelf more ſo towards his Creatures, then all thoſe Relations whatever, according to the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At that day ſhall a Man look unto his Maker, and his Eyes have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto the Holy one of Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 17. 7. And ſo when the Inviſible, God is to us All in All; when we ſee him in all our ways, and in all our goings, in all our Doings and Actions which are ordered by him. As one doth well expreſs it, <hi>When we have wandred all our Ways, Death comes and ſhuts up the Story of our Days.</hi> Even ſo all our Ways, Goings, Doings and Actions, that we Creatures are concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in, it is all, but <hi>Whatever thy hand and thy Counſel determined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be done;</hi> This lays in the ſureſt baſe and beſt Foundation for Patience and Contentment. <hi>I do write the ſame things over again, which to you it is ſafe,</hi> That ye may come to the perfect knowledge, and have the continued remembrance of this ſame Great Truth.</p>
            <p>This Duty of Contentment ſprings up as a Natural Reſult: and Conſequence to what we all owe unto him, <hi>viz.</hi> That we ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God. It is often inculcated and commanded in Scripture, that we ſhould <hi>obey the Voice of God,</hi> or that man <hi>ſhould obey God:</hi> Yea, it is the drift, deſign and tendency of the whole Scripture. As alſo of all our Preaching, that ye may obey God and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in all things. Now that our own will ſhould be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and given up to the Will of God, that our Spirit ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto the Father of Spirits, this is an eſſential part and act of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto God, and herein alſo Contentment doth conſiſt. <hi>Be ſilent, O all fleſh before the Lord, for he is raiſed up out of his Holy Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> Zech. 2. 13. And ſo to be ſilent and to hold our Peace, and to take it quietly whatever it be, to humble our ſelves under the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand of God, <hi>Here is the mind that hath wiſdom, here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints;</hi> This is the very temper and diſpoſition of the Servants of the Lord God.</p>
            <p>Now for the uſe and application of the foregoing diſcourſe, let him, who ſhall hear or read theſe lines ſee well to it, that the ſame mind be in him alſo. Whenſoever we hear good and right things ſpoken of, there let our Hearts and Conſciences be upon the work, upon the examination and application of it all to our ſelves. At the time and place of hearing, How findeſt thou it, O man or woman to be with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> How do ſuch and ſuch good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151376:13"/> things belong to thee? Canſt thou find an Intereſt, Propriety and ſhare in them? Is the bleſſing thine? Why really, here is the Life and Benefit of all Preaching and Hearing, when we can ſay in truth (and without deceit or a lie) of the good things of God, that they are mine. When our Souls can Eccho back, as we hear him Named, that ſaying of <hi>Thomas,</hi> one of the twelve Diſciples, <hi>My Lord, and my God. Thomas</hi> ſpake thus, after he had reached his hand, and thruſt it into the ſide of Jeſus Chriſt who was the <hi>Word.</hi> And ſo Proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, more is the comfort and rejoycing when the words of God reach not our outſide only, but our inſide alſo; and then that Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant which is within (the Soul and Conſcience) doth anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>My Lord, and my God,</hi> here is both Edification and Comfort in this, as alſo it is a moſt Quickening and Powerful Exhortation to do all things, whereby we may pleaſe and approve our ſelves unto our beloved. There are more comfortable words to the ſame purpoſe in this very ſame 20th of <hi>John, Go to my Brethren and ſay unto them, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend unto my Father and your Father, and to my God and your God.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in a moſt eminent manner, he ſhews himſelf to be the firſt born amongſt man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brethren, having infinitely greater Priviledge and Prerogative with the Father. For by expreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing it on that wiſe, <hi>My God and your God,</hi> He doth as it were in the firſt place ſingle out God to himſelf; and then he communicates him forth unto us. If we may here uſe ſuch Plainneſs of Speech, as the Holy Ghoſt doth elſewhere upon like occaſions; It is like carving for ones ſelf in the firſt place, and then helping others. And I am ſure, there is none of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and followers do in the leaſt grudge or think much, that Jeſus our fore-runner (whom <hi>our Soul loves)</hi> ſhould thus in all things have the Pre-eminence; eſpecially ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce that he hath <hi>Purc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſed a Church with his own blood,</hi> he hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e aſſured pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſe, that he ſhall ſee the <hi>travel of his ſoul,</hi> he hath obtain'd of God ſuch inexpreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble <hi>Priviledges</hi> for poor mankind, whoſe Portion before was folly &amp; miſery, ſhame &amp; Death: &amp; thus it is that he doth convey forth thro' his own Life as a Pipe or Conduit, his <hi>Goodneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip &amp; Love to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whom he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſes to call <hi>brethren.</hi> Here is the <hi>ſufficient rejoicing &amp; ſatisfaction to the</hi> reaſonable creature (who doth know &amp; conceive of theſe things) &amp; as much as can be expected on this ſide of heaven. To have the hope &amp; Aſſurance, that our <hi>Creator</hi> is our <hi>Father,</hi> and God is our God; when we can ſay ſo in the <hi>Congregation</hi> and <hi>Communion if Saints;</hi> &amp; each of us particularly hath the voice of God witneſſing from within our ſelves, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is our God. For as he is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac &amp; Jacob,</hi> ſo he is likewiſe the God of all his Saints &amp; ſervants by their ſeveral reſpective Names, who do the works of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and then the neceſſary conſequence is, that all things are ours, if he is our God, who is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Proprietor and Diſpoſer of all things; who hath promiſed and will perform it; <hi>The Lord will give Grace and Glory; no good thing will be with-hold from them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly,</hi> Pſal. 84 11.</p>
            <p>Here ſome may be apt to think, all this is very good; But what is it to the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine of Contentment? It doth pertain and relate thereto, for as there is a certain Band and Connexion, which tyes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151376:14"/> and knits all the ſeveral viſible Parts of the Creation together. So it is, as to the inviſible and future things of God and of his Kingdom. There is a certain Subordination and Connexion of one to another, or one goes before another, and ſo indeed there is of all the Graces and Gifts of the Spirit, and of all the Duties pertaining to Religion. As in the Natural Body of ours, there are Ligatures and Strings, Nerves, Arteries and Sinews, Which do hold the Bones and the ſeveral Parts together: So likewiſe it is the very ſame as to the inviſible Works of God, and what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to the Souls of Men. In the laſt quoted place out of the Pſalmiſt it is ſaid. <hi>The Lord will give Grace and Glory,</hi> the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other; the one here and the other hereafter. And as the Bleſſing and Good Things of God given here in hand, and in this Life are expreſſed throughout all the Old Teſtament by the Word <hi>Peace,</hi> that is to ſay, Peace of Mind and Conſcience, of Soul and Spirit. (Which alſo is confirmed and often mentioned again in the Goſpel, with this Addition and Improvement to it. <hi>The Peace of God which paſſeth all understanding)</hi> What is all this for? So much promiſed by God and ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by his Saints? But becauſe that this ſame thing of Peace was an Earneſt and Aſſurance, a forerunner and certain token of the future and enduring bleſſedneſs, which God would give unto them in the unſeen State. Now under the word Peace, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is alſo included and contained; for they both ſignify near the ſame. But only Peace is much more comprehenſive and extenſive then Contentment. Inaſmuch as Peace chiefly relates to inward Spiritual and Eternal Things; and Contentment is as pertaining to out ward and Temporal things. But ſeeing that to the well Being and Happineſs of the whole Man, there muſt of neceſſity be a Connexion of all things together, in order to render any one in a Good State and Condition. So that as Grace is a Pledge and Forerunner of Glory, true and perfect Peace is a ſure Token of Eternal Salvation: So as it is written, <hi>Who hath Sealed us, and given the earneſt of the Spirit in our Hearts,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 12. Even ſo this Chriſtian Contentment afore-mentioned and afore-treated of is an Earneſt and Seal before hand of that <hi>Reſt which remaineth for the People of God.</hi> So that in order to arrive unto and partake of that reſt hereafter, we muſt come unto and have Contentment here. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which promiſe our Twelve Tribes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly ſerving God Day and Night, hope to come,</hi> Act. 26. 7. As this is the End of all our Religious aſſembling our ſelves together, to worſhip the Lord and hear his word, to ſet us one ſtep yet nearer to it; <hi>So there being a promiſe left us of entring into his Rest,</hi> If you would indeed not come ſhort thereof but enter therein, you muſt of neceſſity do all the Mean and Preparatory Acts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it. See therefore well to it, that ye have either Learned already, or do for the time to come, <hi>Learn in whatſoever State ye are in, therewith to be content.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Written by <hi>RICHARD STAFFORD<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
